A Guide to the Old Dominion Land Company Records, 1829-1948
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Old Dominion Land Company Records, 1829-1948
The Library of Virginia
42587
58 reels of microfilm (Misc. reels 5883-5940)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Loaned for copying by the Newport News Public Library System, 2005-2007.
Alternative Form Available
Originals available at the Newport News Public Library System, Newport News, Virginia.
Biographical Information
During the late 1860's financier Collis P. Huntington's attention was brought to the plight of the debt-ridden Chesapeake and Ohio Railroad which stretched, at that time, from Richmond to Covington, Virginia. In 1869, he and a number of others formed a syndicate to purchase controlling interest in the Chesapeake and Ohio Railroad. Among the men were the brokers Harvey Fisk and Alfrederick Hatch; William Aspinwall, founder of the Pacific Mail Steamship Company; and A.A. Low, clipper ship designer and builder. During the reorganization meeting of the stockholders held on 26 November 1869, Huntington was elected President of the company and General William C. Wickham, Vice-President.
Tradition has it that Huntington had first visited the sleepy village of Newport News in 1837 when he was a traveling salesman. As early as 1870, agents began to quietly purchase land between Richmond and Newport News. They negotiated with local residents or bought auctioned land in James City, York, Warwick, and Elizabeth City Counties. Among those involved with the land purchases were William Aspinwall, his agent Edmund Wilkes, and his attorney William S. Peachy, Sr. Other major purchasers were Alexander B. Green and Collis P. Huntington. In 1872, the decision was made to locate the Atlantic terminus of the Chesapeake and Ohio Railroad in Newport News. Eight years later on 19 October 1880, the Old Dominion Land Company was chartered to secure railway right-of-ways on the Peninsula.
Company officials were: Collis P. Huntington, President; Frank S. Storrs, Secretary; Isaac E. Gates, Treasurer; Theodore Livezey, Superintendent; Agent, C.B. Orcutt; Collis P. Huntington, Abiel A. Low, A.S. Hatch, James H. Storrs, and John Stewart, Directors. Harvey Fisk was also a member of the Land Company.
In 1881, Huntington and the land agents turned over their purchases to the Land Company for $1.00 per parcel. By June of that year, the Land Company had acquired approximately 17,000 acres of land on the Peninsula.
Railroad construction on the Peninsula began in 1880, and the first trains traversed the completed tracks on 16 October 1881, during the centennial celebration of the surrender of Cornwallis at Yorktown. That same year Eugene E. McLean of New York City made the map that determined the eventual layout of the city. Dated 29 April 1881, the map was placed in the records of the Warwick Company Courthouse and lost some time later. McLean was Chief Engineer of the Land Company for many years.
In 1882, the Land Company began work on the Hotel Warwick which was formally opened on 11 April 1882. Destined to play an important part in the development of the city, the hotel was a popular refuge for travelers to the area for decades thereafter. Located on the banks of the James River close to the hotel were a casino, bowling alley, and pleasure pier which provided a great deal of entertainment to both residents and visitors. Until the mid-1930's, the Hotel Warwick's affairs were directed by many of the same officials who were in charge of the Old Dominion Land Company. On 12 November 1935, the Land Company and the hotel were consolidated.
Fulfilling its purpose of developing and selling real estate in Newport News and other areas of the Peninsula, the Land Company distributed a circular to attract new residents and industries in 1883. It had already begun to establish a number of community facilities and by the early 1890's had given land for and/or assisted with the creation of a Union Chapel, Newport News' first bank (the Bank of Newport News, later called the First National Bank of Newport News), the Warwick County Courthouse, schools, and other vital commercial, civic, and government units. Later land donations included the site for Riverside Hospital, the public library and Huntington Park. Either by direct contract or through the influence of the Old Dominion Land Company, a number of piers were constructed newer the terminus of the Chesapeake and Ohio Railroad. In 1883, several passenger piers were built for ferry and steamship companies serving Newport News. Pier "A," at the foot of 25th Street, was designed as a landing place for building supplies and other material and produce for local grocers and businessmen.
In 1886, a shipyard was established as a repair plant for vessels calling at the port. Later to be named the Newport News Shipbuilding and Dry Dock Company, it was built on land owned by the Old Dominion Land Company and directed by some of the Land Company officials including Huntington, Gates, and Orcutt. Land Company officials recognized that a sufficient supply of fresh water was essential to the development of a city. In the late 1880's, they were the moving forces in organizing the Newport News Light and Water Company which remained closely associated with the Land Company from its inception on 8 August 1889, until it was purchased by the city of Newport News in 1926. In 1918, the Light and Water Company entered into an agreement with the United State Government to develop facilities to meet the needs of the expanding population.
Land Company officials were intimately involved in the incorporation of the city. Correspondence in the officers' files reflect a real concern for the proper timing of incorporation so that it would best benefit the company. On 16 January 1896, Newport News became a first-class city and withdrew from Warwick County.
In 1900, Collis P. Huntington died unexpectedly. His interests were passed to his widow Arabella Huntington, his adopted daughter Princess Clara von Hatzvelt, his adopted son Archer M. Huntington, and his nephew Henry E. Huntington, who later married Arabella. Henry Huntington continued his uncle's association with the Land Company. During the second half of the 1910's, the United States Government entered into a number of leases and purchase agreements with the Land Company. Newport News was a major point of embarkation during World War I, and thousands of soldiers were stationed at Camps Hill, Stuart, and Alexander- all built on land owned by the Old Dominion Land Company. After the war, most of these lands were put to other, more peaceable uses.
In 1918, the Land Company established Jefferson Avenue Park, a housing development for black residents. During the 1920's, the Land Company embarked on a major program of residential building- the Huntington Heights subdivision- and also engaged in certifying several other subdivisions including Park View. On 21 October 1925, a group of Newport News men purchased the entire Huntington interests as well as those other stockholders. Throughout the decade of the twenties, there appeared to be a thrust within the company as well as the community to improve the quality of living in the area.
In 1932, nearly all of the income-producing properties had been sold, and Land Company officials were finding new markets for unimproved property. By 1939 the company was liquidated, and the Hotel Warwick was the only valuable piece of property remaining. During the 1940's, the predominance of transactions carried out by the Land COmpany concerned the Hotel Warwick. Liquidation was completed in 1948.
Scope and Content
Records, 1828-1949, of the Old Dominion Land Company of Newport News, Virginia, including records of the Hotel Warwick and Newport News Light and Water Company. The Library of Virginia and Newport News Public Library entered into a partnership to film select records of the Old Dominion Land Company that are housed at the Newport News Public Library System. The collection was not filmed in it's entirety, only select sections of the collection were filmed and are noted in the following finding aid. A copy of the entire original finding aid produced by Newport News Public Library is available: A Finding Aid to the records of the Old Dominion Land Company/Newport News Public Library System [Z1346 .N55 F49]. Also available is, The Map Collection of the Old Dominion Land Company Records/Newport News Public Library System [Z6027 .V81 M29 1982].
The collection was arranged by the Newport News Public Library System and was maintained in the original order set up by the Old Dominion Land Company. The records include abstracts, account books, agreements, by-laws, charters, contracts, correspondence, deeds, journals, insurance policies, inventories, lawsuits, ledgers, menu cards, minutes, newspaper clippings, photographs, reports, stock certificates, and tax records. The papers range from 1829 to 1948 although the bulk of collection consists of the administrative files dating from 1900 to 1930, and the abstracts and deeds dating from 1870 to 1890.
Of particular interest is the documentation of land acquisitions on the Virginia Peninsula. A special enterprise of the Old Dominion Land Company was the Newport News Light and Water Company under whose auspices the Land Company acquired a great deal of watershed property throughout the Peninsula and set up the nucleus of the present day water works owned by the city of Newport News. The abstracts and deeds are also of note because of the invaluable genealogical information and tracing of land holdings.
The collection includes numerous financial reports, journals, and ledgers. Also included are records relating to the Hotel Warwick including correspondence, inventories, insurance, and financial records. Of note is Series X which includes photographs of the interior and exterior of the hotel. The Newport News Light & Water Company records include correspondence, financial records, and copies of lawsuits in which the company was involved.
Although the collection contains a wealth of information there are some areas in which the records are lacking. The collection does not contain administrative files and minute books from the inception of the company nor included are correspondence from Collis P. or Henry E. Huntington. Few records also exist for the Newport News Shipbuilding and Dry Dock Company nor the Chesapeake and Ohio Railroad.
A folder listing is available at the beginning of each reel of microfilm.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Administrative Records in numerical order, 1903-1948
Series II. Administrative Records in alphabetical order, 1893-1948
Series III. Loose Administrative Records, 1871-1947
Series IV. Financial Records, 1881-1949
Series V. Personnel Records, 1926-1947 [not filmed]
Series VI. Real Estate, 1854-1948
Series VII. Maps, 1782-1945
Series VIII. Hotel Warwick Records, 1890-1948
Series IX. Newport News Light and Water Company, 1889-1934
Series X. Miscellaneous Material, 1895-1940
Contents List
- Series I. Administrative Records in numerical order, 1903-1948., Extent: 15 reels (Misc. reels 5883-5897)
  - Suberies 1. Stockholders' Meetings
    - Annual Stockholders Meeting Minutes, 1925-1947. (Reel Misc. reel 5883)
    - Annual Stockholders Meeting Minutes, 1939-1948. (Reel Misc. reel 5884)
    - Annual Reports, 1925-1932. (Reel Misc. reel 5884)
    - Stockholders File, W.T. Chapin, 1926-1927. (Reel Misc. reel 5884)
  - Suberies 2. Directors' Meetings
    - Director's Meeting Minutes, 1925-1947. (Reel Misc. reel 5885-5886)
  - Suberies 3. By-Laws
    - By-laws, Charters, and Amendments, 1911-1935. (Reel Misc. reel 5886)
  - Suberies 4. Financial reports
    - Monthly reports, 1926-1936. (Reel Misc. reel 5887)
  - Suberies 5. Chesapeake & Ohio Railway Company Records
    - Newport News and vicinity, 1909-1940. (Reel Misc. reel 5888)
  - Suberies 6. Farms
    - Aberdeen-McLean Tract, 1903-1936. (Reel Misc. reel 5889)
      Includes agreements, clippings, deeds, and correspondence regarding the purchase of land.
    - Oakland Farm-West Farm and Briarfield Tract, 1903-1936. (Reel Misc. reel 5890)
  - Suberies 7. Federal reports
    - Corporation Income and Excess Profits Tax, 1909-1911. (Reel Misc. reel 5890)
    - Corporation Income and Excess Profits Tax, 1912-1917. (Reel Misc. reel 5891)
  - Suberies 8. Copies of deeds and deeds of trust
    - A-H 1925-1947. (Reel Misc. reel 5892)
    - H-M 1925-1947. (Reel Misc. reel 5893)
    - M-S, 1925-1947. (Reel Misc. reel 5894)
    - T-W 1925-1947. (Reel Misc. reel 5895)
  - Suberies 9. Yorktown Sesquicentennial
    - Correspondence, 1931. (Reel Misc. reel 5895)
  - Suberies 10. Chamberlin Vanderbilt Hotel
    - Correspondence, 1930-1935. (Reel Misc. reel 5895)
  - Suberies 11. Horace E. Dodge Boat & Plane Corp.
    - Correspondence, 1929. (Reel Misc. reel 5895)
  - Suberies 12. James River Bridge
    - Correspondence, 1929-1946. (Reel Misc. reel 5895)
    - Sites at entrance of James River Bridge, 1928-1933. (Reel Misc. reel 5896)
  - Suberies 13. Real estate
    - Quotations, 1917-1936. (Reel Misc. reel 5896)
    - Real estate agents, 1926-1927. (Reel Misc. reel 5896)
  - Suberies 14. Miscellaneous letters
    - A-M, 1926-1934. (Reel Misc. reel 5896)
    - N-Y, 1926-1934. (Reel Misc. reel 5897)
  - Suberies 15. Industrial development
    - Correspondence, 1925-1936. (Reel Misc. reel 5897)
  - Suberies 16. Warwick Laundry
    - Correspondence, 1925-1945. (Reel Misc. reel 5897)
- Series II. Administrative Records in alphabetical order, 1893-1948., Extent: 7 reels (Misc. reels 5898-5904)
  - Suberies 1. Alphabetical files
    - File 1, A-L, 1920-1927. (Reel Misc. reel 5898)
    - File 1, M-Y and File 2 A-K, 1920-1939. (Reel Misc. reel 5899)
    - File 2 L-Y and File 3 B-D, 1926-1947. (Reel Misc. reel 5900)
    - File 3 D-N, 1936-1948. (Reel Misc. reel 5901)
    - File 3 P-W (including Hotel Warwick), 1922-1948. (Reel Misc. reel 5902)
  - Suberies 2. Subject files
    - Auction sale-Insurance agents, 1937-1942. (Reel Misc. reel 5903)
    - C.E. Minniegerode-Myraw Wood and miscellaneous subjects, 1893-1948. (Reel Misc. reel 5904)
- Series III. Loose administrative records, 1916-1939., Extent: 1 reel (Misc. reel 5905)
  - Board of Directors Minute Books, 1916-1921; 1928; 1928-1939. (Reel Misc. reel 5905)
- Series IV. Financial records, 1881-1948., Extent: 5 reels (Misc. reels 5906-5910)
  - Suberies 1. General Accounts
    - Journal No. 1, 1881-1887. (Reel Misc. reel 5906)
    - Journal No. 6, 1917-1921. (Reel Misc. reel 5906)
    - Journal No. 8, 1924-1926. (Reel Misc. reel 5907)
    - Journal No. 9, 1926-1936. (Reel Misc. reel 5907)
    - Journal, 1936-1948. (Reel Misc. reel 5908)
    - Ledger No. 1, 1881-1889. (Reel Misc. reel 5908)
    - Ledger No. 5, 1913-1925. (Reel Misc. reel 5909)
    - Ledger No. 6, 1926-1935. (Reel Misc. reel 5909)
  - Suberies 2. Stockholders and investments
    - Correspondence, 1914-1942. (Reel Misc. reel 5910)
- Series V. Personnel records, 1926-1947.
  No records from this Series were filmed.
- Series VI. Real estate, 1828-1948., Extent: 13 reels (Misc. reels 5911-5923)
  - Early land agent correspondence and transactions, 1870-1884. (Reel Misc. reel 5911)
    Includes correspondence of William Aspinwall, A.B. Green, and correspondence dealing with land purchased on the Virginia Peninsula.
  - Abstracts of titles. (Reel Misc. reel 5912)
    Tracts include: Burkes, Melson farm, Rich Neck, Log Landing, Charles Jones, Briarhurst, Cooke and Gibbs, Taylor Farm, Ivy, Washington Lodge, Stony Point Farm, and Queen's Creek.
  - Abstracts of titles. (Reel Misc. reel 5913)
    Tracts include: William Lee Farm, McLean, Burk Farm, Downey Farm, Brooks or Lee, Wynne property, Skinner, Log quarter, Weymouth, Bailey's, Merry Oaks, Wilbern Farm, W.J. Hawkins, Mount Airy, D.S. Jones, and Lots 27-28, 33-36, and 193.
  - Deeds, 1828-1869. (Reel Misc. reel 5914)
  - Deeds, 1870-1879. (Reel Misc. reel 5915)
  - Deeds, 1880-1881. (Reel Misc. reel 5916)
  - Deeds, 1882-1895. (Reel Misc. reel 5917)
  - Deeds, 1896-1910. (Reel Misc. reel 5918)
  - Deeds, 1911-1925. (Reel Misc. reel 5919)
  - Deeds, 1926-1948. (Reel Misc. reel 5920)
  - Leases, agreements, and related correspondence, 1892-1948. (Reel Misc. reel 5921)
  - Articles of agreements, contracts, and related papers, 1877-1947. (Reel Misc. reel 5922)
  - Contracts, bids, and correspondence dealing with Huntington Heights, 1925-1938. (Reel Misc. reel 5923)
- Series VII. Maps, 1782-1945., Extent: 2 reels (Misc. reels 891-892, Accession 31552)
  Maps in this collection were those used by the Old Dominion Land Company in its devleopment of Newport News, the surrounding counties of Elizabeth City, James City, Warwick, and York, and areas of the neighboring city of Hampton. The diverse contents range from municipal plans and land surveys to architectural and civil engineering plans.
- Series VIII. Hotel Warwick Records, 1890-1948., Extent: 14 reels (Misc. reels 5924-5937)
  - Suberies 1. Numerical Administrative records
    - Records, 1928-1948. (Reel Misc. reel 5924)
  - Suberies 2. Miscellaneous Administrative records
    - Records, 1927. (Reel Misc. reel 5925)
  - Suberies 3. Correspondence
    - Correspondence, 1926-1947. (Reel Misc. reel 5925)
  - Suberies 4. Contracts
    - Contracts, 1900-1942. (Reel Misc. reel 5926)
  - Suberies 5. Insurance
    - Insurance, 1927-1941. (Reel Misc. reel 5926)
  - Suberies 6. Personnel
    - Personnel and pay roll account, 1937-1947. (Reel Misc. reel 5926)
  - Suberies 7. Finance
    - Account book, 1928-1943. (Reel Misc. reel 5927)
    - Account book, 1928-1943. (Reel Misc. reel 5928)
    - Journal No. 2, 1938-1943. (Reel Misc. reel 5929)
    - Journal No. 3, 1943-1947. (Reel Misc. reel 5929)
    - Fund Book No. 3, 1945-1947. (Reel Misc. reel 5929)
    - Voucher Record Book No. 9, 1946-1947. (Reel Misc. reel 5929)
    - Balance sheets, 1927-1930. (Reel Misc. reel 5930)
    - Comparative Statement of Expenses, 1931-1932. (Reel Misc. reel 5930)
    - Inventories, 1941-1943. (Reel Misc. reel 5930)
    - Financial statements, 1931-1933. (Reel Misc. reel 5931)
    - Financial statements, 1933-1935. (Reel Misc. reel 5932)
    - Financial statements, 1936-1939. (Reel Misc. reel 5933)
    - Financial statements, 1940-1941. (Reel Misc. reel 5934)
    - Daily reports, 1936-1939. (Reel Misc. reel 5935)
    - Transcript of Guest Ledger, 1940-1941. (Reel Misc. reel 5936)
    - Daily Steward Report to Manager, 1933-1934. (Reel Misc. reel 5937)
    - Miscellaneous financial papers, 1890-1948. (Reel Misc. reel 5937)
    - Miscellaneous, Sample menu cards, 1946-1948. (Reel Misc. reel 5937)
- Series IX. Newport News Light & Water Company Records, 1889-1934., Extent: 3 reels (Misc. reels 5937-5939)
  - Suberies 1. Administrative records
    - Records, 1889-1913. (Reel Misc. reel 5937)
      Includes bills to legislature, charters, and index to Minute book No. 1.
    - Officers' correspondence, 1894-1916. (Reel Misc. reel 5937)
    - Cremation, sale of company coupons and certificates, 1917-1934. (Reel Misc. reel 5937)
    - Motor Vehicle titles, 1920-1924. (Reel Misc. reel 5937)
  - Suberies 2. Correspondence
    - Enlargement of water facilities, 1918. (Reel Misc. reel 5937)
    - Water supply to Camp Stuart and other places, 1918. (Reel Misc. reel 5937)
    - Naval Mine Depot, 1920-1925. (Reel Misc. reel 5937)
  - Suberies 3. Finance
    - Financial statements and inventories, 1902-1903. (Reel Misc. reel 5937)
    - Inventories and real estate assessments, 1904-1926. (Reel Misc. reel 5938)
  - Suberies 4. Legal matters
    - Newport News Light & Water Company vs. W.I. Nelms, 1892. (Reel Misc. reel 5938)
    - Newport News Light & Water Company vs. Commonwealth of Virginia, 1905-1906. (Reel Misc. reel 5938)
    - Commonwealth of Virginia at the relation of the Newport News Light & Water Company vs. City of Newport News and others, 1920-1924. (Reel Misc. reel 5938)
    - Newport News Light & Water Company tax protests, 1926-1929. (Reel Misc. reel 5938)
  - Suberies 5. Property
    - Rentals, 1892-1897. (Reel Misc. reel 5938)
    - Proposal to build reservoir, 1906. (Reel Misc. reel 5939)
    - Report on standing timber and land, 1913. (Reel Misc. reel 5939)
  - Suberies 6. Miscellaneous
    - Minute Book No. 1, 1889-1913. (Reel Misc. reel 5939)
    - Meter book and list of water pipes in Hampton, ca. 1900. (Reel Misc. reel 5939)
- Series X. Miscellaneous Material, ca. 1916-1950., Extent: 1 reel (Misc. reel 5940)
  Consists of approximately 40 photographs of the Hotel Warwick and Hilton Village in Newport News, Virginia. The photographs have been digitized and are available online. Click here to search the Newport News Public Library Photograph Collection online.
  - Photographs, ca. 1916-1950. (Reel Misc. reel 5940)
    Includes images of the Hotel Warwick, Newport News waterfront and buildings, Camp Hill, and Petersburg development.